<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The intentions of the army plainely discovered, in a dispute betweene Major Generall Browne, and Major Scot, an Independent, concerning the King. Wherein is manifested how much they regard the honour and safety of his Majesties person. As also the occasion and manner of the late difference betwixt the said Major Generall Brown, and Colonell Whaley. Certified in a letter from Wooburne, dated July 31. 1247 [sic].</title>
            <author>G. R.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91929</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E400_37</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201767</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862267</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862267</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114420</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91929)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114420)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 63:E400[37])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The intentions of the army plainely discovered, in a dispute betweene Major Generall Browne, and Major Scot, an Independent, concerning the King. Wherein is manifested how much they regard the honour and safety of his Majesties person. As also the occasion and manner of the late difference betwixt the said Major Generall Brown, and Colonell Whaley. Certified in a letter from Wooburne, dated July 31. 1247 [sic].</title>
                  <author>G. R.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: G.R.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 3".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Browne, Richard, --  Sir, 1602?-1669.</term>
               <term>Scott, Thomas, d. 1660.</term>
               <term>Whalley, Edward, d. 1675?</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114420:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE INTENTIONS OF THE ARMY Plainely diſcovered, IN A Diſpute betweene Major Generall <hi>Browne,</hi> and Major <hi>Scot,</hi> an Independent, concerning the King.</p>
            <p>Wherein is manifeſted how much they regard the honour and ſafety of his Majeſties Perſon.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO The occaſion and manner of the late difference betwixt the ſaid Major Generall <hi>Browne,</hi> and Colonell <hi>WHALEY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certified in a Letter from <hi>Woobourne,</hi> Dated <hi>July</hi> 31. 1247.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1647.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:114420:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114420:2"/>
            <head>The Intentions of the Armie plainely diſcovered.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Made you promiſe, faithfully to give you the account of what my obſervation in the Court and Campe might hold worth your intelligence; you may juſtly expect the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance: The King, whom alwayes the greatneſſe of his Spirit and Reſolution holds undaunted, beares it firme above the injurie of Threatning, and remains unterrified: however, Major <hi>Scot,</hi> an Independent Member (yet deſerves ſomething to hang on) lately, &amp; in the preſence of the King, being asked by Major G. <hi>Browne,</hi> what good end they would make in the Houſe, made a deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate ſudden reſolution, They could never make a good end, till they took
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114420:3"/> off the Kings heads that ſtood there to whom Major Gen. <hi>Browne</hi> replyed; I had thought, Sir, you had come to have kiſſed the Kings hand: Sir, ſaid Major <hi>Scot,</hi> I had rather follow him to the Gallowes; and I think he ſpoke the ſenſe and intention of the Armie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and what is ordinarily belcht out in their Drink, when men in over-charged ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks vomit out truth in the naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their hearts. The Ma. General immediatly addreſſeth himſelfe to his Majeſtie, made him knowing of that deſperate language, takes <hi>Scot</hi> by the ſhoulder, ſaying, Sir, this is the man: the King, whom ever higheſt Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and his own innocence with mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle protects, ſlights the madneſſe and malice of ſo poyſonous a tongue.</p>
            <p>Sir, I ſhall adde one thing more, ſince I have ſo good occaſion to name a man of ſo much integritie and Honor. You
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114420:3"/> may have heard imperfectly the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel between Major Gen. and Col. <hi>Wha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley;</hi> I ſhall give you a perfect relation, and which <hi>Whaley</hi> himſelfe dares not denie: The Commiſſioners and Col. <hi>Whaley</hi> being ſet at Dinner, <hi>Whaley</hi> took an occaſion to tell the Major Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, he knew well he was an enemie to their proceedings: indeed he reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he was, and muſt openly declare to the world, he hated the baſeneſſe of their intentions. Sir, ſaid <hi>Whaley,</hi> had Sir <hi>Tho. Fairfax</hi> been ruled by me, our Army ſhould have marched up to the Citie, and have ſhaken their Gold Chaynes: then, Sir, ſaid the Major Generall, you intend by this to plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Citie, as you have droven away the Members; but if they were all of my minde, and at unitie within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs, we would not care for five times your Army (and as we are, we regard
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114420:4"/> you not) we would draw out, and fight with you in the field: What, ſaid the Colonel, with a companie of Coblers, Tinkers, Tapſters, &amp; Tankard-bearers; I know not, ſaid the Ma. Gen. but you may have ſuch in your Army, &amp; there is none but hath: to whom <hi>Whaley</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, but Runners for their Officers; <hi>Eſſex</hi> and <hi>Maſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y's</hi> reformers: Sir, ſaid Ma. Gen. <hi>Browne,</hi> let me tell you, there are as gallant brave gentlemen among them as any in your Army, and have fought as bravely &amp; gallantly: you wil expect ſome, ſaid <hi>Whaley;</hi> to whom the Ma. Gen. replyed, None: yes, one or two, ſaid <hi>Whaley;</hi> not your Generall, quoth Ma. <hi>Browne:</hi> I tel you, ſaid <hi>Wha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> they are Runners. Ma. Gen. at the repetition not a little moved, replyed, By God, Sir, you lye, and I will make it good with my ſword; and know you, that nothing but your ſword ſhal give
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114420:4"/> me ſatisfaction: and whereas you think your Command will countenance you to affront men (for he had juſt told him he would remove him from his place) I will fight with you in the face of your three Regiments. Sir, I am a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen &amp; a Reformiſt, and hold my ſelf concerned in your language, and will maintaine thoſe Gent. as gallant as any in your Army, and will my ſelfe fight with your Generall; let him draw up his whole Army and engage that not a man do me violence but himſelf. The contention was high, Col. <hi>Whaley</hi> not over-forward to draw, yet his hand on his hilt, was eaſily with-held by the company, and certainly Ma. Gen. was not behind-hand: the King had notice of it, &amp; took up the difference betwixt them. You ſhall doe well, to let thoſe Gen. know, how much they are ingaged to the courage of that gallant &amp; honeſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114420:5"/> man, ſeriouſly as hee carries on every thing with high regards to his honor; in this he did not out doe himſelfe. His gallantry and Reſolution is emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently known, and though his courage flye high, yet never to leſſening, ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted and well tempered a minde he beares. Sir, I hold you too long, I beg your pardon, give me leave to tell you, I expect no good from this Army but by accident, intentionally deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the K. &amp; P. the liberty they take of language, the unreaſonablenes of their demands, &amp; all for themſelvs, give ſmall encouragement to hope a good end by them, yet I wonder they ſhould ſo openly ſpeak their thoughts of deſtroying the King, as if Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy were ended in him, whoſe nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Royall Iſſue gives enough to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, we can be happy in no other Government.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>VVoobourne,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iuly</hi> 31.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed> Your humble Servant, <hi>G. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
